Mss.B.H435p Mss.B.H435p Mss.B.H435p
American Philosophical Society
Sir John F. W.(John Frederick William) Herschel correspondence, 1793-1874
Mss.B.H435p
American Philosophical Society
40.0 Item(s)
This collection concerns astronomical observations, earthquakes, meteorology, photography, physics, professional associations, publications, and scientific instruments. The correspondents include Augustus De Morgan, Dionysius Lardner, Sir Francis Beaufort, and Sir Edward Ryan.
40 items.
Herschel, John F. W., Sir, (John Frederick William), 1792-1871
Box 1
Related Archival Materials note
There is also correspondence (1836-1868, 19 items) with Sir Charles Lyell in the Lyell Papers in the American Philosophical Society Library (see PAAV87-A166).
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Purchased from Amram and accessioned, 12/--/1956. See in-house shelf list for additional accession numbers and dates.
Biographical/Historical note
Sir John Frederick William Herschel (1792-1871) was an astronomer and prominent member of several British scientific societies of his day.
J. F. W. Herschel was born at Slough, England, March 7, 1792. His father, Sir William Herschel, was a renowned astronomer. After studying at Dr. Gretton’s School at Hitcham, and at Eton, J. F. W. Herschel was educated at home by a mathematician by the name of Rogers. Herschel graduated as Senior Wrangler from St. Johns College, Cambridge at the age of seventeen. He founded, along with George Peacock and Charles Babbage, the Analytical Society of Cambridge – an intellectual discussion group which encouraged its members to “do their best to leave the world wiser than they found it.” In 1813 Herschel was elected a fellow of the Royal Society.
In 1814 he entered as a student at Lincoln’s Inn to study law. He turned, however, to science. He reported in his journal on the 10 September, 1816 that he is “going under my father’s direction to take up stargazing.” Herschel distinguished himself in astronomy for the rest of his life.
Herschel co-founded the Royal Astronomical Society, and served two terms as president, starting in 1827. In 1829 he married Margaret Brodie. In 1831 he was knighted. Of particular scientific interest to Herschel were double stars and sun spots. He made numerous advances in the development of telescopes and microscopes, as well as the fields of magnetism and optics. He published one hundred fifty two papers and was a trustee of the British Museum.
J. F. W. Herschel died in 1871 and was buried in Westminster Abbey near the grave of Sir Isaac Newton.
Early American History Note
This manuscript collection falls outside the geographic scope of the Early American guide (British North America and the United States before 1840). It may be of interest to scholars interested in global history, international relations, imperialism, or the U.S. in the world.
Beaufort, Francis, Sir, 1774-1857; De Morgan, Augustus,1806-1871.; Lardner, Dionysius, 1793-1859; Ryan, Edward, Sir, 1793-1875; Astronomy.; Beyond Early America; Earthquakes.; Meteorology.; Photography -- Early works to 1850.; Physics.; Science -- Societies, etc.; Scientific apparatus and instruments.
- Papers
  - Letter to Mr. Gerning, London, Jan. 6, 1793; 9-1/8x7-1/4; Herschel, [Sir] W[illia]m, 1738-1822.
    Scope and Contents note
    Slough, Eng., A.L.S. 1p.add.end. Info. about a book. Inform Prof. Schmidt that Newtonian telescope is ready.
    Not Found: 3/14/2011
  - Epitaph on..., 1817; 12-3/4x7-3/4; Herschel, John F. W. (John Frederick William), Sir, 1792-1871
    Slough, Eng. A.M.S. 1p. Epitaph, in verse, to his sister?, with a sketch.
  - Letter to ---., 25 April, 1820; 9x7 1/2; Herschel, John F. W. (John Frederick William), Sir, 1792-1871
    ALS. 4p. illus. with typescript. Explores polarizing of light in crystals and other polarizing experiments. 1. Newton, Sir Isaac, 1642-1727. 2. philosophical Society, Cambridge. 3.
  - Letter to ----, Nov., 1821; Herschel, John F. W., Sir, (John Frederick William), 1792-1871
    [received] Xerox of A.L.S. 2p.,end. Recommends Henslow for post at Trinity. NOT TO BE QUOTED OR COPIED.
  - Letter to [Dinoysius Lardner], Aug. 18, 1823; 10x8; Herschel, John F. W. (John Frederick William), Sir, 1792-1871
    A.L.S. 3p.and add. Concerning his publications. Suggests Whewell for crystaleography and Fitton for geology. Plates of optical department to be uncolored.
  - Letter to Dionysius Lardner, April 30, 1827; 9x7-1/2; Lardner, Dionysius, 1793-1859. Herschel, [Sir] J[ohn] F[rederick] W[illiam], 1792-1871.
    A.L.S. 3p. Praises Airy. Concerning works on calculus.
  - Letter to Dionysius Lardner, July 25, 1828; 9x7-1/2; Herschel, John F. W. (John Frederick William), Sir, 1792-1871
    A.L.S. 3p. M,ght contribute an article on light. Is finishing an article for the encyclopaedia.
  - Letter to J[ames] Hudson, [Sec. of Royal Society], London, June 27/28, 1831; 7x4-1/2; Herschel, John F. W. (John Frederick William), Sir, 1792-1871
    Slough, Eng., A.L.S. 3p.add. Gives references for tables of Italian measures.
  - Letter to D. Robertson, Westminster, February 15, 1833; 9x7¼; Herschel, John F. W. (John Frederick William), Sir, 1792-1871
    A.L.S. 2p. add., end. Acknowledges that "the contingencies of a long residence in so distant a Part of the world may very well render it extremely inconvenient to retain my name on the tracts in question".
  - Letter to the Albany Institute, Albany, N.Y., Sept. 30, 1836; Herschel, John F. W., Sir, (John Frederick William), 1792-1871
    Cape of Good Hope, South Africa, A.L.S. 3p.and add.,end. Thanks for meteorological observations and suggests method for constants in making such observations. Hopes they will continue, and send them to him at the Royal Society next year.
  - Letter to "Sir", November 30, 1837; 9x7½; Herschel, John F. W. (John Frederick William), Sir, 1792-1871
    A.L.S. 2p. Asks correspondent to expedite the shipping of the remaining portion of Smith's collection as "it is more desireable that in the ensuing spring months the Exhibition should be made as complete and attractive as possible."
    General note
    See: (Herschel papers.)
  - Letter to the Earl of Melbourne, London, August 27, 1838; 9-3/4x8; Herschel, John F. W. (John Frederick William), Sir, 1792-1871
    Newcastle on Tyne. A.L.S. 1p., add., enc. wanting. Sends copy of resolutions passed by the British Association. Will meet with him "for the purpose of affording every explanation of the reasons which have weighed with the Association in their adoption".
  - Letter to John Stewart, London, 14 Jan., [18]39; 9 x 7 1/2; Herschel, John F. W. (John Frederick William), Sir, 1792-1871
    Slough, A.L.S. 4p. add. end. Makes arrangements to see Gassiot's battery exper., if schedule permits. Has Royal Soc. business. Would like to see Babbage. Family new. Mentions James Grahame.
  - Letter to Capt. [Sir Francis] Beaufort, Aug. 1, 1839; Herschel, John F. W., Sir, (John Frederick William), 1792-1871
    A.L.S. 3p.and add. Concerning observations, based on lacaille's law. Maclear's comments of assistants available.
  - Letter to Tho[ma]s Thomson, June 13, 1844; 5¼x4¼; Herschel, John F. W. (John Frederick William), Sir, 1792-1871
    Collingwood, A.L. in 3rd 2p., add., enc. wanting. Takes the liberty to forward a few specimens of Tritonia Uvaria. Explains their care and flowering schedules. Mentions Steuart.
  - Letter to -, April 16, 1846; 5x4½; Herschel, John F. W. (John Frederick William), Sir, 1792-1871
    A.L.S. 1p., end. Fragment. Extends compliments to his correspondent's wife "in which my wife begs to join".
  - Letter to "Dear Sir", December 30, 1847; 7½x4½; Herschel, John F. W. (John Frederick William), Sir, 1792-1871
    Collingwood, A.L.S. 2p. Concerns Gerhardt's collecting of Leibniz correspondence. Mentions Encke.
  - Letter to ----, April 18, 1850; 6x4; Herschel, John F. W. (John Frederick William), Sir, 1792-1871
    Collingwood, A.L.S. 3p. Expresses thanks for an invitation to the British Association meeting at Edinburgh. Refers to Captain Jacobs; mentions heliometer.
  - Letter to J. Buckley, Exeter, September 21, 1853; 7x4½; Herschel, John F. W. (John Frederick William), Sir, 1792-1871
    A.L.S. 3p. and env. Herschel comments on a meteor described by Buckley.
  - Letter to "My dear Sir;", Jan. 17, 1854; 7x4-1/2; Herschel, John F. W. (John Frederick William), Sir, 1792-1871
    A.L.S. 3p. Letter on the death of "the Marshall" arrived too late so could not attend funeral.
  - Letter to ----, July 24, 1859; Herschel, John F. W., Sir, (John Frederick William), 1792-1871
    Collingwood, (?) A.L.S. 1P. Has no alterations to suggest for any of the plates.
  - Letter to [Sir Edward?] Ryan, April 16, 1860; Herschel, John F. W., Sir, (John Frederick William), 1792-1871
    Collingswood, A.L.S. 3p. Concerning Willy's appointment and the need for good administration in the position.
  - Letter to "My dear Sir Henry;", Dec. 16, 1862; 7x4-1/2; Herschel, John F. W. (John Frederick William), Sir, 1792-1871
    A.L.S. 4p. Concerning Herschel's translation. Enjoyed Sir Henry's book on physical geography of the sea [Gulf Stream], etc.
  - Letter to ----, Jan. 1, 1863; Herschel, John F. W., Sir, (John Frederick William), 1792-1871
    Collingwood, A.L.S. 3p. His views on earthquakes.
  - Letter to "My dear Sir", May 31, 1865; 7¼x4½; Herschel, John F. W. (John Frederick William), Sir, 1792-1871
    Kent, A.L.S. 3p. Concerns wave lengths.
  - Letter to ----, June 23, 1865; 7x4-1/2; Herschel, John F. W. (John Frederick William), Sir, 1792-1871
    A.L.S. 4p. States that the article is not worthy of publication in its present form.
  - Letter to "Dear Sir", Nov. 3, 1866; 7x4½; Herschel, John F. W. (John Frederick William), Sir, 1792-1871
    Collingwood, A.L.S. 2p. Asks whether he should ask Brayley to write a review of a book he received sometime ago. Mentions the London Institution and Alexander Stewart Herschel.
  - Letter to A[ugustus] DeMorgan, London, Oct. 6, 1870; 3-1/2x4-3/4; Herschel, John F. W. (John Frederick William), Sir, 1792-1871
    Collingwood, A.L.S. on postal card. 1p. and add. Asks a series of riddles of his correspondent.
  - Letter to ----, June 22, 1871; 6-1/4x4; Herschel, John F. W. (John Frederick William), Sir, 1792-1871
    A.L.S. 3p. Vision. Concerning underwater use of cameras.
  - Letter to "Dear Sir", Oct. 23, 1874; Herschel, John F. W., Sir, (John Frederick William), 1792-1871
    A.L.S. 2p.
  - Astronomical Notes, Undated
    A.D. 2p.
  - Letter to ----, Undated; Herschel, John F. W., Sir, (John Frederick William), 1792-1871
    Monday, 18th. A.L.S. 3p. Concerning copper content in the ore.
  - Letter to "My dear Sir", Undated; 7x4½; Herschel, John F. W. (John Frederick William), Sir, 1792-1871
    A.L.S. 2p. Preparations for a forthcoming voyage prevented him from dining with the Royal Society Club.
  - Letter to "Dear Sir"., Undated; 7¼x4½; Herschel, John F. W. (John Frederick William), Sir, 1792-1871
    A.L.S. 2p. Concerns Herschel's thoughts on salary matters.